Okay so today's דף daf. *daf* is פ"ז *pezayin*, we're a little
behind. We start right after the משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* on פ"ז עמוד
ב' *pezayin amud bais*. We had just we had just read that
if you שוחט shocheit. *shecht* many animals, many חיות *chayot* or many
birds at the same time, you just cover the blood once. You
don't have to do it between each one. If you did it
with any... raise the cost of poultry, if you did חיה chaya
*chaya* and עוף of. *oph* at the same time, then there's an
opinion of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* that you cover them
separately. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. תנו רבנן
tanu rabanan, *Tano rabanan*: חיה chaya *chaya*. It says if you capture
or you know a חיה chayah. *chaya*, so כל *kol*. כל משמע
חיה chayah. *kol mashma chaya*. Everything means חיה chayah, *chaya*. בין מרובה
בין ממועט *bein meruba bein memu'at*. Whether many or whether one. Meaning
חיה chayah, *chaya* does not mean a singular חיה chayah *chaya*, it
means as a sort of class.
Fowl, let's say I say fowl, sheep, fowl. Right, it means whether
you're talking about one or whether you're talking about many. חיה chayah
*chaya*, whether one, whether many. עוף *oph*, fowl, כל משמע *kol mashma*.
It means all cases. כל משמע עוף *kol mashma oph*, everything is
implied by עוף *oph*. בין מרובה בין ממועט *bein meruba bein memu'at*.
Whether many whether few. מכאן אמרו *mikan amru*, from here they said:
שחט shacht מאה חיות במקום אחד *shachat me'ah chayot b'makom echad*, if
you've slaughtered many חיות *chayot* at one place, many deer let's say,
כיסוי kisuy. אחד לכולם *kisui echad l'kulam*. Just cover the blood once.
You know, at the end of it all. מאה עופות במקום אחד
*me'ah ophos b'makom echad*, many birds in the same place, כיסוי kisuy
אחד לכולם *kisui echad l'kulam*, covered all at the end. חיה ועוף
במקום אחד *chaya v'oph b'makom echad*, even birds and חיות *chayot* in
the same place, כיסוי kisuy. אחד לכולם *kisui echad l'kulam*, covered all
at the end. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer, *Rabbi Yehuda omer*,
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says: שחט shacht חיה יכסנו *shachat
chaya yechasena*, no, if you're doing both birds, fowl and חיה *chaya*,
then cover them separately. Slaughter your חיה *chaya* and cover it, ואחר
ישחוט את העוף *v'achar yishchot es ha-oph*, and then the birds. שנאמר
*shene'emar*, חיה או עוף *chaya o oph*, it says חיה *chaya* or
birds, which means treat them separately. אמרו לו *amru lo*, they said
to him: הרי אומר *harei omer*, the verse says: כי נפש כל
בשר דמו בנפשו הוא *ki nefesh kol basar damo b'nafsho hu*, which
is or is it he? דמו בנפשו היא *damo b'nafsho hi*, I
think it might be. Anyway, that's right after the verse about covering
the blood, and therefore it says דמו *damo* in okay, so what
does that mean? מאי קמהדרי ליה *mai ka-mahadrei lei*? What type of
a response is this? How does that address the question of his
position of separating חיה *chaya* and עוף *oph*? הכי קאמרי ליה רבנן
*hachi ka-amrei lei rabanan*, this is what the רבנן *rabbis* are saying.
האי או *hai o*, you say the או *o* is needed to
separate חיה *chaya* and עוף *oph* to say do them separately. No,
מיבעי ליה לחלק *miba'ei lei l'chaleik*. You need it to tell me
that you cover even if it's just חיה *chaya*, even if it's
just עוף *oph*, it's not only if you slaughtered them both together.
מיבעי ליה לחלק *miba'ei lei l'chaleik*. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah *Rabbi
Yehuda*, what would רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* say back? לחלק
*l'chaleik*? No, no, no, to separate them: מדמו נפקא *mi-damo nafka*. It
says its blood, singular, so that means that even if it's only
one, only חיה *chaya* or only עוף *oph*. So since you get
from the singular that you only need one, what do I get
from the או *o* that separates them? To say that you cover
them separately. So רבנן *rabanan*, what would the רבנן *rabbis* say back?
דמו טובא משמע *damo tuva mashma*. No, דמו *damo* doesn't mean only
its one animal's blood. דמו *damo* means can also mean like their
blood, can mean many animals.
Would it be דמם *damam*?
Well, דכתיב *dichsiv*, but it sort of means sort of if you
speak about it as a class. דכתיב *dichsiv*: כי נפש כל בשר
דמו בנפשו היא *ki nefesh kol basar damo b'nafsho hi*, the soul
of all flesh, its blood is in the soul. So since there's
all flesh,
except you know, as we know in English grammatically also all is
in the singular, right? Well, everyone is singular,
everyone here
must take his גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you'd be in the singular. All
I don't know, anyway.
What about, you know, the singular is y'all, so what's the plural?
All y'all. All y'all.
That's a good one. All right, anyway, so anyway, so somehow they
say based on this verse which says all flesh and it uses
the singular, you would not have said singular meant
would have told you either חיה *chaya* or עוף *oph*. So therefore
you needed the או *o* to tell you you don't need both,
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says you use the או
*o* to tell you you cover them separately. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* goes on. אמר רבי rebbi חנינא *amar Rabbi Chanina*, said
רבי rebbi, חנינא *Rabbi Chanina*: מודה היה רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda לענין
ברכה bracha, שאינו מברך אלא ברכה bracha אחת *modeh hayah Rabbi Yehuda
l'inyan beracha she'eino mevareich ela beracha achas*. You only make one ברכה
bracha *beracha*, which is interesting, right? It's still one מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*.
Now, and therefore you would only make one ברכה bracha *beracha*, even
though there may be the nature of the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to
cover the blood separately of חיה *chaya* and עוף *oph*, it's still
not a separate מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. You could actually frame that in
two ways. Meaning, what happens if I do two מצוות mitzvos *mitzvos*
one right after the other? Do I make one ברכה bracha. *beracha*
or two ברכות berachos *berachos*? Maybe if they're one right after the
other, maybe I only make one ברכה bracha? *beracha*. It's hard to
think of a scenario where I do two מצוות mitzvos *mitzvos* one
immediately following the other, because once I've done one, I've then I'm
done with my obligation. I'm trying to think about a scenario where
I would do that. Maybe I blew the שופר shofar *shofar* for
one person and then I went ahead right again and blew the
שופר *shofar* for another person. I don't know, I'd have to think
about it. But anyway, one possibility is even if you call them
two מצוות mitzvos, *mitzvos*, maybe if you do them
sequentially. More likely what it's saying is it's one מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*.
The nature of the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is that you cover the bloods separately of חיה
*chaya* and עוף *oph*, but it's still one מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* and
therefore you make one ברכה bracha. *beracha*. So like שחיטה shechita *shechita*?
I mean the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* didn't mention anything about שחיטה shechitah?
*shechita* in this connection.
Oh, well שחיטה shechitah. *shechita* is a good point, that's true. I
mean again, if you consider each שחיטה shechitah. *shechting* of each animal
that if I had separated them I would make separate ברכות brachos,
*berachos*, and then if I that's a good point, right. So I
mean that's a little different. because it's not a מצוה mitzvah like
I get you know a שכר מצוה. sachar mitzvah. What exactly the
nature of the ברכות brachos. of שחיטה shechitah, is, is it more
of a מתיר, matir, is it more of a שבח? shevach? But
that's like a nice example. Or let's say here's a great example,
let's say I'm a מוהל mohel and I've got a lot of
yesterday we had a ברית bris of twins, right? So let's say
but it wasn't but it was only one of them was the
ברית. bris. So let's say I've got multiple babies I'm doing assembly
line 10 people have same day, right I would make one ברכה,
bracha I could in theory make one ברכה bracha and then do
all the ברית מילות. bris milas. So in theory if you do
sequential ברכות, brachos you would actually sequential מצוות mitzvos. you would make
one a you know one ברכה bracha. not separate ברכות. berachot. I
believe, I have to double check, but I believe that's the case.
But more simply what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying is is
that it's one ברכה bracha. one מצוה mitzvah with but you the
nature of the מצוה mitzvah is you cover the blood separately and
therefore you only make one ברכה. bracha. אמלי רבינא לרב אחא בריה
דרבא, Amlei Ravina le-Rav Acha brei de-Rava, so said רבינא Ravina to
רב אחא Rav Acha the son of רבא, Rava, ואמלי רב אחא
בריה דרבא לרב אשי, ve-amlei Rav Acha brei de-Rava le-Rav Ashi, some
say רב אחא Rav Acha said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, מאי
שנא מהמידי דרב, mai shna me-hamidei de-Rav,
one minute, why do you make only one
ברכה? bracha. How's it different than the following story of the students
of רב? Rav? Now the question is going to be not whether
conceptually we see this as one מצוה mitzvah. or not, but the
fact that according to רבי Rebbi יהודה you actually separated the two.
What did you do to separate the two? You covered the blood
between them, right? You did an act of covering the blood after
you שחט'ד shachted the חיה before covering the עוף. Shouldn't that basically
be essentially a הפסק, hefsek, right? So therefore even if let's say,
you know, whatever the scenario is, if I was doing multiple מילות
milas in that case, but if there was a הפסק hefsek between
them, I'd make another ברכה. bracha Okay, here too, you know, there's
a הפסק, hefsek, you're going to go ahead even if if you
didn't have a הפסק hefsek you could say you're doing one מצוה
mitzvah for all, but when you do have a הפסק, hefsek, shouldn't
that mean that you did two separate מצוה mitzvah acts? Shouldn't that
define it as now two separate מצוה mitzvah. acts and not only
two separate מצוה mitzvah acts, but two separate מצוה mitzvah acts for
which one ברכה bracha. doesn't work because it is separated by a
הפסק? hefsek? And if there's a הפסק, hefsek, the ברכה bracha can't
apply to something that comes afterwards after a break. Let's just see
the question why it's a
הפסק. hefsek. דרב ברונא ורב חננאל תלמידי דרב הוו, De-Rav Bruna ve-Rav
Chananel talmidei de-Rav havu, רב ברונא Rav Bruna and רב חננאל Rav
Chananel were the students of רב, Rav, I'm sorry, הוו יתבי בסעודתא,
havu yasvi bi-seudata, they were they were sitting at a meal. קם
עלייהו רב ייבא סבא, Kaya alaihu Rav Yeba Saba, רב ייבא סבא
Rav Yeba Saba the elder was there and he was sort of
serving them, he was the שמש. shamash. So even though he was
older than them, I guess still, you know, they were the bigger
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim or he needed the פרנסה, parnassa, whatever it
was, he was the one that was that was being the waiter
at the meal. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, so they said to him,
הבו נברך, havu nvarech, come let's בנטש bench because they wanted to
come presume maybe even include him in the זימון, zimun, because you
could include the שמש, shamash, you know, the waiter in the זימון.
zimun. So הדר אמרו ליה, hadar amru lei, then they said what
moment, הבו נשתי, havu nishrei, wait wait we changed our mind, go
bring some more wine. They were having too good of a time.
So אמר להו, amar lehu, so he said back to them and
this I get thinking a little ironic here he's the waiter and
he's saying back to them, אמר להו רב ייבא סבא, amar lehu
Rav Yeba Saba, הכי אמר רב, hachi amar Rav, whoa buddies, here's
what רב Rav said, so now he's teaching them the הלכה, halacha,
כיון דאמרו הבו נברך, keivan de-amru havu nvarech, as soon as you
said come let us בנטש, bench, איתסר ליה למשתי חמרא, itzlei le-mishtei
chamra, you can no longer drink wine. So therefore you made a
הפסק. hefsek. When you said רבותי נברך, rabosai nevarech, that's a הפסק.
hefsek. And now you can't go back to eating. Now, there's an
interesting תוספות Tosafos that says really can't go back to eating? Let's
say you want to make another ברכה. bracha. Okay, it means you
can't go back to eating without another ברכה. brachah, But you at
least have the הפסק hefsek and you'd have to make another ברכה.
brachah. תוספות Tosafos actually has a question and this is I'm not
going to get into this, what degree of a הפסק hefsek is
something that if you want to now resume eating, you just have
to make another ברכה ראשונה, bracha rishona, but and what degree of
a הפסק hefsek is something that you would have to actually בנטש
bench and then start again. תוספות Tosafos is inclined to think that
most of the time even if it's a הפסק, hefsek, you don't
actually have to בנטש, bench, you just now have to make another
ברכה ראשונה bracha rishona and at the end your one בנטשינג benching
can go for everything. But he sort of has a question, maybe
there's some times it's a big enough הפסק hefsek that you even
have to, you know, בנטש bench and finish the previous thing before
you resume. Regardless, our point is is that once there was a
statement of come let us בנטש, bench, that's just a הפסק hefsek
and you have to at least make another beginning ברכה. brachah So
here too shouldn't the covering be essentially the same thing?
I see there's some questions what does that mean ברכה brachah, on
another item or can it be something that you just ate and
you want
to no no no, even if you're drinking the same cup of
wine, right, here they did say let's drink maybe give us some
more wine, but but no, even if it's the same thing, as
soon as you said let us בנטש, bench, that's like you're saying
I'm done eating. And now if you want to resume, you have
to make another ברכה. brachah? Hold off the questions, let's just see
where the גמרא Gemara ends because I'm sure you could think of
some distinctions but the גמרא Gemara, is going to make a distinction.
So הכי נמי, hachi nami,
כיון דאיתסר ליה לכיסוי, keivan de-itzlei le-kisui, here too once you had
to attend to covering the blood, איחייב ליה בברכה, ichayev lei be-bracha,
you have to make the ברכה brachah on the new thing because
you basically are saying you're done with the old thing. So גמרא
Gemara says הכי השתא, hachi hasha, what type of a comparison is
that? התם hasam משתי וברוכי בהדי הדדי לא אפשר. mishtei u-vruchei be-hadei
hadadi lo efshar. There you can't be drinking while you're making the
ברכה. brachah. Didn't your mother always tell you not to eat not
to talk while you're eating? So הכא, hacha, here, אפשר דשחי בחדא
ומכסי בחדא. efshar de-shachi be-chada u-mechasi be-chada. If you're ambidextrous you can
שחט shacht, with one hand while you're covering with the other, so
the covering is not a contradiction. Now, take this גמרא Gemara literally,
what the גמרא Gemara is just saying is is it physically possible
to do both. If it's not physically possible to drink and make
a ברכה, brachah, so saying הב לן ונבריך, hav lan nivreich, let's
sort of start בענטשן, benching, and the indication that you want to
start בענטשן, benching, it says puts the drinking aside because it's not
physically possible to drink at that time. Whereas since it's physically possible
to שחט shachting while you're covering, it's not a הפסק. hefsek. תוספות
Tosafot does not like that read of the גמרא, Gemara. although it
sounds like what the גמרא Gemara is saying. תוספות Tosafot actually quotes
somebody who says, let's say in the middle of בענטשן, benching, you
got up to דאווענען. davening. In the middle of eating you got
up to דאווענען. davening. Then when you go back to eating, you're
not going to have to say מנחה Mincha or something. When you
go back to eating, you would have to make another ברכה. brachah
Why? 'Cause you can't דאווען daven and eat at the same time.
So תוספות Tosafot says, I don't understand. And if you talk during
eating, or תוספות Tosafot has another case. Let's say you heard thunder
and you stopped to make a ברכה brachah on the thunder during
eating. So since you can't eat while you're making that ברכה, brachah
so now you have to make another ברכה? brachah So תוספות Tosafot
says, it's not about whether you're physically able to or not. It's
the fact that when you say הב לן ונבריך, hav lan nivreich,
that that is the end of eating. The fact that you've signaled
you're ready to בענטש, bench, בענטשן benching is what you do after
eating. So you're basically have said you are done eating. Okay, so
then if that's so, anything, if you just סתם stam do some
physical activity that you can't do simultaneously, it's not a הפסק. hefsek.
So if that's true, why did the גמרא Gemara have to, what's
the reason of distinguishing that from the covering of the blood? So
תוספות Tosafot says, so I would have said the following: I would
have said that that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara means. It means
that when you say let us בענטש, bench, בענטשן benching is the
end of eating. Since when is covering the blood the end of
necessarily a process of שחיטה? shechitah Meaning, I, you know, okay, I'm
covering that blood but I still might be involved in שחיטה. shechitah
And therefore, and maybe it's trying to sort of demonstrate that by
saying you could even in theory do them at the same time.
But the emphasis is not the physical possibility. It's saying that covering
blood is not so much of an end of a process the
same way בענטשן benching is. תוספות Tosafot doesn't say that. תוספות Tosafot
says actually no, that exactly is what bothered the גמרא. Gemara Because
after you שחט, Shachat you cover the blood. So covering actually is
what showed you're done with your process of שחיטה. shechitah, It comes
at the end of שחיטה, shechitah, the same way בענטשן benching comes
at the end of eating. So that's why the גמרא Gemara actually
made the comparison. And the גמרא Gemara said yes, it's not just
the physical activity of covering the blood. It's that covering the blood
really signals that you're done with שחיטה shechitah and now it's something
new. So therefore the גמרא Gemara said, ah, but even though that
does signal it, since it is still possible at least in theory
to do covering and שחיטה shechita at the same time, it's not
the same degree the end of the process the same way בענטשן
benching is the end of the process of eating. So the upshot
of all of this is what? Do you have to make another
ברכה brachah when you interrupt the process? Yes. But what constitutes an
interruption? So the way תוספות Tosafot understands the upshot of the גמרא
Gemara. is the only thing that constitutes an interruption is number one
an activity that really signals the end of the previous activity, that
really says we're done, which would be בענטשן benching and maybe covering
the blood. And even there, תוספות Tosafot says, you know, if it
doesn't fully signal that like covering the blood, which is not fully
excluding the continuation of שחיטה, shechting then it is not an interruption
and then you do not make a ברכה. brachah So even רבי
Rebbi יהודה that has you stop and do a covering would still
say that it's not an interruption and you would the same and
and you could make one ברכה, brachah you know, that one ברכה
brachah would go for the second, what you're going to do is
you're going to make the first ברכה bracha on the covering when
you cover the דם החיה, dam hachayah, and then you're going to
resume. But the continuing and the resuming and whatever, that is not
considered an interruption.
Even if you walk out of the room?
Even if you, yeah. That is, I mean okay, there are always
those questions about how much, when would you have a הפסק? hefsek?
How much time? How much היסח הדעת? hesech hadaat? We're not to
fully figuring that out. I would say that תוספות Tosafot has in
another discussion, what's a הפסק hefsek for שחיטה, shechting. because you were
asking the whole שחיטה shechita. question. Right? If you're שחט shecht many
animals and what type of an interruption. And that gets תוספות Tosafot
a whole conversation, right, about, and this is an important question, about
you know you have two models and the question is which model
something falls in. You have the model of תפילין, tefillin, which is
if you make a ברכה bracha, on the של יד shel yad
and then you interrupt between that speak between that and the של
ראש, shel rosh, you have to make a another ברכה bracha, on
the של ראש. shel rosh. Meaning even אשכנזים Ashkenazim who make a
separate ברכה bracha. on the של ראש shel rosh of על מצות
תפילין, al mitzvat tefillin, if they interrupt between של יד shel yad
and של ראש shel rosh have to make two ברכות berachot, on
the של ראש, shel rosh, להניח lehaniach as well. So the ברכה
bracha להניח lehaniach on the של יד shel yad only goes on
the של ראש shel rosh if there's no interruption. On the other
hand you have other scenarios where even if you interrupt once you
got started you don't make another ברכה bracha as long as it's
not a complete interruption. So for example
you're checking for חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach night and you say
על ביעור חמץ, al biyur chametz, that's a common example, and then
you stop and actually have to you know I don't know say
get me a flashlight or this or that or maybe even if
you have to answer the phone in the middle and then you
go back, once you started, right, then the and then you continue,
it's much harder to define that it's an interruption and the same
ברכה bracha would continue. So the question is which is the rule,
which is the exception? תוספות Tosafot is inclined to think that the
תפילין tefillin is the exception, that that's really one מצוה mitzvah and
a small interruption would break it. But you know in those but
whereas other things you know maybe it's more of like a continual
process or it's multiple things strung together and does not need to
be as tightly combined. And then תוספות Tosafot has a whole conversation
about what type of a הפסק hefsek between different שחיטות. shechitot. acts
of שחיטה shechita, would be consider- would demand that you make another
ברכה bracha. if you're שחיטה shechita, like you know you go to
the Empire, whatever, there's the whole day there's שחיטה. shechita. So what
stage do they when they go to the bathroom in the middle
they come back and make another ברכה, bracha when they stop for
lunch, if they answer their cellphone, right? Those are questions. So okay,
that's a whole שיעור shiur by itself, but he raised- he doesn't
have clear conclusions but he raises those questions. Yes. I'm wondering how
much it would be the same as- the point you were catching
up from the summer about שיעור shiur in your שהייה shehiya שיעור
shiur I was listening to this morning where you discussed the שיעור
shiur for שהייה shehiya and the שיעור shiur that causes הפסק hefsek
is simply the זמן zman that it takes to do the activity.
What struck me is it doesn't take long to put on תפילין,
tefillin, so it makes sense that it's
so short, but in the other example, it makes sense but... Sometimes,
sometimes, but that's not the only- first of all, how you define
just pausing as an interruption and what the שיעור shiur of pausing
is, varies from case to case, although you're right generally it's true
that we look at how long it takes to do the activity,
but תוספות Tosafos is not saying that. תוספות Tosafos is saying even
if it's- even if it's the same type of break, the sense
is by תפילין, tefillin, you know,
automatically you make the ברכה, bracha other things breaks don't demand another
ברכה. bracha So it's not just whether it constitutes a break or
not. All right? So yes, I'm not giving answers here, I'm just
sort of laying out what the issues are, though. Yeah.
This is a bit of a digression I guess, but how did
the idea of an interruption become so strongly associated with a verbal
interruption?
Right, that is a good point. And the whole point about yes,
and you know, is speech- speaking, you know, more of a הפסק
hefsek than just pausing and so on, so it is a bit
of a digression, but it's true that it is, that speaking is
considered more, even more than like gesturing or something like that, or
you know, I don't know, like to do a מלאכה, melacha, I
can talk about turn on the lights, and somehow that's seen as
less- it could be that a lot of times when we're talking
about interruptions, we're talking about interrupting speech acts. So- interrupting my דאווענען,
davening, interrupting my- I'm sure you- you'd think that if you ask
for a flashlight during בדיקת חמץ, bedikas chametz, that's not an interruption.
Right, but that's another question, by the way, right? לצורך מצוה. letzorech
mitzvah. My father wouldn't- wouldn't, you
know, wouldn't utter a word. Really? Oh, that is interesting. That is
interesting. So yeah, yeah, it- it- there's definitely material on that but
I'm
not prepared to give an answer to that,
I'd have to review it. But I would say, by the way,
an exception in general to rules of
interruption is something that is לצורך letzorech that מצוה. mitzvah So for
example, although this isn't exactly the same about a מצוה mitzvah. process,
but after you wash hands and
you're not supposed to talk till you make
המוציא, Hamotzi, you could say please pass the knife or please pass
the salt or whatever. Not after you make the ברכה bracha before
you eat, that has a different sort of thing, that's- but you
understand, every- every different thing has different parameters. Yes. Okay, let's go
back to the- no, and we're going to talk about that in
the next משנה. mishnah, Yes, so my question was about the רבותי
נברך. Rabosai nevarech. Yeah. So you know when you're- we'll say- let's
בנטש, bentch, then you do שיר המעלות, Shir Hama'alos, then you do
רבותי נברך. Rabosai nevarech. So when you mean רבותי נברך Rabosai nevarech
or even beforehand, we're saying, 'Alright, you know, come guys, let's- you
know.' So even if you said it in the vernacular 'Let's בנטש',
bentch that effectively is רבותי נברך. Rabosai nevarech. Even if you didn't-
haven't done שיר המעלות Shir Hama'alos or anything like that? Correct. Okay.
Yeah. I mean, you know, and that raises questions, like you know
at what constitutes 'let's בנטש'? bentch You say come on everybody, let's
get going or whatever, you know, what stage? Yeah, so those do-
those do raise הלכה halacha questions at what stage does that essentially
constitute a הפסק? hefsek? Anything after you basically בנטש, bentch, even before
רבותי נברך. Rabosai nevarech. Yeah. But if- I mean, if you said,
'Come on, I'm in a rush, we gotta go,' whatever, that might
not be the same. But if- but if you say, 'Come on,
let's בנטש', bentch that's essentially רבותי נברך, Rabosai nevarech, you know? Yeah.
Okay, let's move on. I- I will just point out again, although
I said let's move on, one other way in which it's not
exactly similar, the comparison, which is, the ברכה bracha that talked about
before was the ברכה bracha? on the drinking. The בנטשינג bentching is
an end to the drinking and then you make another ברכה. baracha,
Here, the ברכה baracha, was not the ברכה baracha. on the שחיטה.
shechita The גמרא Gemara wants to say, that would have been a
more- am- apt comparison, a ברכה baracha on the שחיטה, shechita something
that interrupts the שחיטה, shechita covering blood, you need to make another
ברכה bracha on the שחיטה. shechita Right? That would have been the
more direct comparison. Here, the ברכה beracha you're making is on the
כיסוי. kisuy So it's really what really- you know, is not saying
that you're still in the middle of the שחיטה shechita that started
before. What we really have to say is the שחיטה shechita? that's
coming after is not a הפסק hefsek between this כיסוי kisuy. and
that כיסוי. kisuy So conceptually it's not exactly the same, but okay,
that being noted, let's move on.
Okay, next משנה, mishnah, פז עמוד א.
Pez amud aleph. שחט shecht next- next משנה, mishnah. רבי Rebbi יהודה
שחיטה shechita perforce. Yeah, it strikes me that it's talking on the
כיסוי דם kisuy dam like that, because perforce what do you- mandate
by having to have a separate כיסוי kisuy is that you have
two separate שחיטה shechitah. lines. You can't שחט shechted a chicken and
a חיה in the same מקום, makom, the same place, with the
דם dam going to mix. Right, unless you interrupt each act with
a כיסוי. kisuy? That's how you would do it. You'd interrupt each
act. Perforce saying you can't שחט shecht both. Right. Which is why
the גמרא Gemara is- well, right, right, without interrupting that. Right. Let's
take a look at the משנה. mishna. שחט ולא כיסה. Shachat velo
kisa. So here's David's question. Somebody שחט and did not cover the
blood, וראהו אחר, verao acher, and somebody else saw him, חייב לכסות.
chayav lechasos. So the other person has to cover it. It's not
just your individual obligation. Exposed blood, you know... Exposed blood has to
be covered, which, you know, is a fascinating question, like which types
of things are מצוות mitzvot on the individual, which types of things
relate to the situation and the situation needs to be addressed. This
question's about we looked at discussing ברית מילה, bris milah, you know,
to what degree yes the obligation is primarily on the father, but
if the father doesn't do it, then to what degree is the
fact that there's a non-circumcised child in the community revert let's say
a communal obligation or the obligation on the child or something that
it relates to the problem about the situation the state of affairs
rather than that have to be addressed, rather than just the personal
obligation. Let's see your argument. What? It's not ערבות. arvus. It's not
like if you didn't do a מצוה mitzvah I'm responsible for your
מצוה. mitzvah It's like it directly becomes related to everybody else's obligation.
It would be a ביטול עשה, bitul asei, not like right, right.
The meat is kosher. כיסה ונתגלה, kisa venisgala, let's say you covered
it and then it got exposed, פטור מלכסות, patur milachasos, you don't
have to cover it again, which is a little ironic given the
past point because now the blood is exposed. But once the מצוה
mitzvah was done, it's over and now exposed blood is not a
problem. So it's not that anytime you see exposed blood, I mean
if I saw exposed blood that was not based on שחיטה של
חיה ועוף shechita shel chaya va'of I also wouldn't have to. So
it's exposed blood that has not had the מצוה mitzvah of כיסוי
done to it. Okay, something, right. Okay. כיסהו הרוח, kisa'u haruach, if
it was covered by the wind, then there was not the מצוה
mitzvah was not done to it, חייב לכסות, chayav lechasos, you still
have to cover. Now of course it's a little bit strange. What's
the point of covering something that's already covered? So the גמרא Gemara,
is going to say that maybe it gets re-exposed. Okay, while it's
not exposed, there's no obligation. But if it gets uncovered somehow, then
since there was never the מצוה mitzvah done to it, then it
requires to be covered. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
So the last position in that earlier גמרא gemara is inconsistent with
this משנה. mishnah In what way? Because it talks about ambidextrous. Yeah.
I mean, oh, because it focused on the person. No, because we
still want to because still the primary obligation resides with the person,
the שוחט. It's only if he doesn't satisfy, he doesn't do his
obligation, then it becomes more distributed. Because he could have an assistant.
Right. So you but but the גמרא gemara, I think had to
say that since we first look at things in terms of the
person who's obligated, right, he's obligated. If he doesn't do his obligation,
then we talk about who else. So if he, the person who's
obligated, could not be doing both at the same time, then that
might describe it as a interruption in the process. The primary way
we look at it is through the person who's obligated. All right,
so let's take a look. תנו רבנן, ושפך וכיסה, veshafach vechisa, you
shall spill the blood and cover it with dirt. Actually, it's בעפר,
be'afar, it's with dust. Okay. מי ששפך יכסה. mi sheshafach yechaseh. So
first we say the one who spills covers. That's the primary obligation.
שחט ולא כיסה, shachat velo kisa, he shechted and didn't cover, וראהו
אחר, vera'ahu acher, and somebody else saw it, מנין שחייב לכסות, minayin
shechayav lechasos, how do you know the other one has to cover?
שנאמר ואומר לבני ישראל, shene'emar va'omar livnei yisrael, and I said to
the children of Israel, you know, דם כל בשר לא תאכלו. dam
kol basar lo socheilu. That's the next פסוק. pasuk. Don't eat blood.
So since it juxtaposes it with and I said to the children
of Israel, to like a collective declaration, so therefore אזהרה לכל ישראל,
azhara lechol yisrael, all of the Jewish people are are commanded regarding
this מצוה. mitzvah It's also a communal responsibility. So it starts with
the individual who's obligated, but if he shirks his responsibility, then it
reverts to a communal responsibility. Okay, no, let's read a little more.
תניא אידך, tanya idach, we taught another ברייתא, braisa, ושפך וכיסה, veshafach
vechisa, you shall spill and cover. So this is a different point.
ושפך, veshafach, במאי ששפך בו יכסה. bemai sheshafach bo yechaseh. Do the
covering with the same thing you do the שחיטה shechitah with. שלא
יכסנו ברגל. shelo yechasenu beregel. Don't sort of like just kick dirt
over it, which would be a natural thing to do. Why? שלא
יהיו מצוות בזויות עליו. shelo yiheyu mitzvos bezuyos alav. You should not
treat מצוות, mitzvot you know, denigrate מצוות. mitzvot So therefore, you know,
it's like you know using your foot to kick on something, you
know, it might be convenient and you don't mean to denigrate, but
still it's not respectful that you do a מצוה mitzvah, by like
kicking dirt. So therefore do it in a more respectful way. It
doesn't necessarily mean you pick up the dirt with your hand, you
could use a shovel, but at least do it in a way,
do it in a way that shows respect towards the act that
you are doing. Now it's interesting that the גמרא, gemara okay fine,
so that's that actually becomes then a general principle of, you know,
of do things in respectful manners. Now the גמרא Gemara says, we'll
get back to you in a second Michael, תניא אידך, tanya idach,
we taught another ברייתא, braisa, going back to our idea our story
about about whose מצוה mitzvah? it is. ושפך וכיסה, veshafach vechisa, וכיסהו,
vechisa'u, right? Anyway, מי ששפך הוא יכסנו. mi sheshafach hu yechasenu. The
one who spills is the one who should cover it. מעשה באחד
ששחט וקדם חברו וכיסה. ma'aseh be'echad sheshachat vekadam chaveiro vechisa. Somebody once
shechted and somebody else jumped ahead and grabbed the opportunity and covered
the blood. וחיבו רבן גמליאל, vechiyavo raban gamliel, and רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel obligated the guy that jumped ahead in line and that took
the מצוה mitzvah. away from this person, ליתן לו עשרה זהובים, liten
lo asara zehuvim, give ten gold coins, which is a not trivial
amount of money, I don't know exactly how much it is, but
it's at least a hundred dollars if not more, to this person
who you stole the מצוה mitzvah from. It was his מצוה mitzvah
and you grabbed it away from him. איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, they
raised the question, שכר מצוה או שכר ברכה. sechar mitzvah o sechar
bracha. Are you paying him for stealing the מצוה mitzvah or paying
him for stealing the ברכה? beracha, It's funny, you think the מצוה
mitzvah. *mitzvah* is the bigger deal. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
למאי נפקא מינה *le'mai nafkuh minnah*, what difference does it make? לברכת
המזון *L'birchas hamazon*, let's say somebody stole from somebody else a בענטשינג
*benching* opportunity. So that is four, that's four ברכות berachot *brachos*, right?
Leading the זימון zimmun? *zimmun*, that's four ברכות *brachos*. So אי אמרת
שכר מצוה mitzvah אחת היא *ei amart s'char mitzvah achas hi*, if
it's שכר מצוה mitzvah, *s'char mitzvah* that was only one מצוה mitzvah.
*mitzvah* he stole. ואי אמרת שכר ברכה bracha *ve'ei amart s'char bracha*,
that it's the ברכה *bracha*, הויין ארבעים *haveyan arbaim*, it would be
he would have to pay, it's interesting it switches from one to
40, but it means 40 gold coins. Okay, it's doing the ten
coins thing. Now actually the פוסקים *poskim* say that we don't mean
any סתם *stam* א ברכה *a bracha*, because actually they're involved a
little bit. There's another גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that says גדול העונה יותר
מן המברך *gadol ha'oneh yoser min hamevarech*. So what does it mean
to steal a ברכה *bracha*? So they actually give two answers. One
answer is that is that they said it quietly so nobody else
could answer אמן amen. *amen*, which is then hard to see in
the בענטשינג *benching* case because obviously if you're בענטשינג *benching* for זימון
zimmun, *zimmun*, people have to answer אמן amen? *amen*. Or they say
that no, no, no, obviously we mean not just סתם *stam* stealing
a ברכה *bracha*, you know, but we mean when you are grabbing
a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* from somebody, do we weigh sort of the
severity of stealing the מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* based on just it was
one מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* act, or if there are multiple ברכות *brachos*
associated with the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, that increases the severity. So it's
not just the ברכה *bracha* per se, but it's a way of
measuring the weight of the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. That I think makes
it a little bit better also, not just in terms of answering
this question of גדול העונה יותר מן המברך *gadol ha'oneh yoser min
hamevarech*, but because it's hard enough to understand this fine for stealing
a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*, but to סתם *stam*, a fine for stealing
a ברכה *bracha* seems a little out of proportion. So this at
least approaches saying no, that's a sort of an index towards, you
know, the weight of of when you steal a ברכה *bracha*, a
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. Let's see the end and then I'll take all
questions because I'm sure people have questions. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this, מאי *mai*, so what's the resolution? תא שמע
*Ta shma*, come and hear, דאמר ליה ההוא צדוקי לרבי *de'amar lei
hahu tzaduki l'Rebbi*, a certain Sadducee. I forgot to check the, probably
has it here, probably the original is מין min? *min*, cause it's
מין min *min*? Yeah, yeah, I was sure it was מין min,
*min*. Okay, which again means, you know, probably traditionally meant Jewish Christians,
which I as we've seen before, the מינים *minim* sort of, you
know, are in the same conversation. And you know, יעקב מינאה *Yaakov
minah*? Yeah, exactly. Anyway, so he said לרבי *l'Rebbi*: מי שיצר הרים
לא ברא רוח *mi she'yatzar harim lo bara ruach*, the one who
created the mountains didn't create the wind, ומי שברא רוח לא יצר
הרים *u'mi she'bara ruach lo yatzar harim*, and vice versa, דכתיב *dichshiv*,
the verse says: כי הנה יוצר הרים *ki hinei yotzer harim*, behold
the fashioner of mountains, ובורא רוח *u'vorei ruach*, and the creator of
of wind. So you see it's different it's different creators. אמר ליה
amar lei, *Amar lei*, he said back to him: שוטה *shoteh*, idiot,
שפיל לסיפא דקרא *shfil l'seifa de'krah*, go look at the end of
the verse. ה׳ צבאות שמו *Hashem tzevaot shemo*, his name is the
Lord God, so you see it's only one. So again, one wonders,
right, if this whole idea of spirit and wind, right, and the
whole sense of light, the you know, the Christian idea of the
Holy Spirit, you know, if that's if that's part of sort of
the subtext here. That's what I was wondering, and maybe specifically the
use of the word בורא *borei*, which is
like to fashion, so says
more of a sort of a יש מאין *yesh mei'ayin* type of
a thing, whereas not a יוצר *yotzer*, I don't know. A lot
of it is שלא כמשנה *shelo kamishnah*. Right, that also. Anyway, there
that was their debate. I have a sense that there was something
else going on with that. You know, at minimally also it was
an argument, these are classic arguments you know for the Trinity is
that you sort of see indicators of different you know different forces,
it's not all singular, it's not all a single God. Anyway, so
that I have a sense that's part of what's going on here.
Anyway, so that was their exchange. אמר ליה amar lei, *Amar lei*,
נקוט לי זימנא תלתי יומי ומהדרינא לך *nekos li zimna tlati yomei
u'madveina lach*. He said, give me three days, that was a good
answer, give me three days, I want to get back to you
on that. That's what the מין min, *min* said to רבי Rebbi
*Rebbi*. I'm going to get back to you on that. Okay, ומהדרינא
לך תיובתא *u'madveina lach tyuvta*, I'll give you I'll I'll respond to
you with a challenge. So יתיב רבי תלתא תעניתא *yasiv Rebbi tlata
ta'anisa*. So רבי *Rebbi* sat in three תעניתים *ta'aniseim*, three fasts, presumably
three days he fasted, that this person should not be able to
have a challenge, you know, the whole idea of these sort of
disputations of the Middle Ages, right, which obviously a lot was at
stake that, so presumably that was some of what was going on
here. And seemed to be again, not just a question about a
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, you know, but
a real you know profound theological
issue, clearly even if you bracket the Christian aspect, clearly what he's
arguing about is the nature of God, right? So whatever the whole
background is. Anyway, so רבי *Rebbi* was very concerned. So he sat
sat three fast days that he should be able to have a,
you know, to have a good response to this guy. כי הוה
קא בעי מברך *Ki hava ka'ba'ei mevarech*, now some have the גירסא
girsa *girsa* which is probably better למיברא *mivra*, when he wanted to
either do ברכת המזון *birchas hamazon* or sit down to eat probably
which is probably makes more sense. אמרי ליה *Amrei lei*, people said
to him: צדוקי קאי אבבא *tzaduki kai a'bava*, oh that מין min,
*min* is at the door, or there's a מין min *min* at
the door. So he thought it was this guy that he was
arguing with. So אמר *amar*, he said: ויתנו בברותי ראש *vayitnu bivrosi
rosh*, they have given in my meal, that's why the word probably
למיברא *mivra*, בברותי *bivrosi* in my meal, ראש *rosh* poison. Here I
am finally I'm finally finished my תענית *ta'anis*, right, remember he had
been sitting in a תענית *ta'anis*. So finally today's תענית *ta'anis* was
over, I'm finally wanting to eat and now I have to deal
with him. Okay, anyway, אמר ליה amar lei, *amar lei*, so the
מין min. *min* came in and said, רבי *Rebbi*, it was a
different מין min. *min*. He said רבי, מבשר טובות אני לך. mevaser
tovos ani lacha. Wait, wait, I'm here to tell you good news.
לא מצא תשובה אויבך, lo matza teshuvah oyvecha, your enemy did not
find a way to respond to you, ונפל מן הגג ומת, v'nafal
min hagag v'met, and he fell off of the roof and he
died. שלום על ישראל. shalom al yisrael. Okay, so good news all
around. But yeah, I know. So אמר ליה, amar leh, I understand.
What's a מין? min, Well, it is a question, if מין min,
does mean the Jewish Christians, there was different degrees in which they
were oppositional to the rabbis or not. Some of them were very,
at least initially, very positive relations to the more sort of rabbinic
Judaism. Anyway, okay. Okay, so אמר ליה, so he said to this
מין, רצונך שתסעוד אצלי? retzoncha shetis'ad etzli? Oh, great! Now I can
sit down and eat. Would you like to come and eat with
me? So אמר לו, amar lo, הן. hen. He said, "Sure, why
not?" לאחר שאכלו ושתו, l'achar she'achlu v'shatu, after they ate and drank,
אמר ליה, כוס של ברכה אתה שותה? kos shel baracha ata shoteh?
He said to him, "What would you rather? Would you rather drink
the cup of ברכה, או ארבעים זוזים אתה נוטל?" o arbaim zuzim
ata notel? רבי said to the מין, "Would you rather drink the
cup of ברכה, או ארבעים זוזים אתה נוטל? o arbaim zuzim ata
notel? Would you rather get 40 gold coins?" So אמר לו, amar
lo, he said back to רבי, כוס של ברכה אני שותה. kos
shel baracha ani shoteh. I'd rather drink the cup of ברכה. So
meaning that here's somebody that really respects the Judaism and the מצוות
mitzvos. and the opportunities. Maybe it was a little bit of a
test. תוספות tosafot actually said that he really he wanted he didn't
want to offer the bentching to the מין, but he didn't think
he could just ignore him because he had done such a favor,
so he actually wanted to buy him off and to give him
this offer, and this guy was so much like לשם שמיים l'shem
shamayim that he'd rather do the כוס של ברכה, kos shel baracha,
right, exactly. He'd rather do the כוס של ברכה kos shel baracha
than take 40 gold coins. יצתה בת קול ואמרה, yatzta bat kol
v'amra, a heavenly voice came out and said, כוס של ברכה ישווה
ארבעים זוזים. kos shel baracha yishveh arbaim zuzim. From here on in,
the opportunity of the cup of ברכה is worth 40 gold coins.
אמר רבי יצחק, amar rebbi yitzchak, and רבי יצחק rebbi yitzchak said,
עדיין ישנה לאותה משפחה, adayin yeshnah l'otah mishpacha, that family of that
מין still exists בין גדולי רומי, bein gedolei romi, is amongst the
important families of Rome. וקורין אותה משפחת בר לויאנוס, v'korin otah mishpachat
bar lavyanus, and it's known as the family of Bar Lavyanus, which
I have no idea if that has a Latin phrase that means
something. Does what's his name say anything? Does שטיינזלץ steinsaltz give any
what לויאנוס lavyanus might mean? No, but he has an alternate version
from the סביא לוליאנוס. savya lulyanus. לוליאנוס. lulyanus. Does he give any
meaning to that though? Okay. Question? Yes, Michael. So I had a
question, is the מצוה mitzvah of כיסוי for the same people who
are obligated in שחיטה? shechitah Let's say a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh v'katan went and covered the blood, is it not considered a
good כיסוי? You mean do we treat it like other מצוות so
that if
you're not a בר חיובא, bar chiyuva, you have
the מצוה, mitzvah does it automatically become a communal מצוה? mitzvah That's
a nice question. Because you're right, a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh
v'katan with observation could
do a kosher
שחיטה and I mean the משנה mishna. before spoke about if you
see them you're חייב לכסות chayav l'chasot but it didn't speak about
whether they're חייב לכסות. chayav l'chasot. So if they want to, would
they do they have the right to do it first essentially? That's
a nice point. That's a very nice point. It's not like they
have to מוציא motzi somebody else but is it considered an I'll
get back to you on that. That's a very nice question. Yeah,
Dave. Do we know anything here about the scope of people who
we can include in זימון? zimmun. That's the גמרא Gemara, in ברכות.
You mean but here he's a מין. Yeah, so does that make
him like an אפיקורוס? apikoros? Well no, the real גירסא is מין.
Does that make him like an אפיקורוס apikoros and on the basis
of that exclude him? Yeah, that's an interesting question. Well I will
say that the whole idea that אפיקורסות, apikorsus, heresy as opposed to
issues about observance excludes people is really not in the גמרא, Gemara
it's really much more in the רמב"ם rambam and then it gets
adopted more from the רמב"ם. rambam. I mean the גמרא Gemara does
have nice things to say about אפיקורסין apikorsin and מינין, minin, but
as a basis of exclusion that really comes much more from the
רמב"ם. rambam. The other point and maybe I'll sort of say it
here is that it's actually the text is a little ambiguous because
it says כוס של ברכה אתה שותה. kos shel baracha ata shoteh.
Why didn't it say כוס של ברכה אתה נוטל? kos shel baracha
ata notel? So actually and רש"י, rashi, if you look at רש"י,
rashi, there's a funny רש"י. rashi. רש"י rashi says שכר ארבע ברכות
שאני אחריהם אמן, schar arba brachos she'ani achreihem amen, that he responded
אמן. amen So it sounds like רש"י rashi like he was giving
him the opportunity to answer to the bentching and to drink the
כוס של ברכה. kos shel baracha. And he says, "Look, do you
want to leave for the bentching, we'll do it without you?" It's
a funny scenario. "Right, leave for the bentching or would you like
to be present for the bentching and drink the כוס של ברכה
kos shel baracha and answer אמן?" And he wanted to be present.
So that way it's very different. He's not leading, but then it's
also bizarre. So even to answer אמן is a thing that's worth,
you know, 40 זוזים? zuzim? That's very much against the whole sense
we had before which it was about who's doing who's saying the
ברכה who's leading the מצוה. mitzvah So anyway, but I did want
to put out there's discussion around that and around the text of
are you going to drink rather than do you want to lead
the bentching. So it might be that he actually was just responding.
But even even if you... Right, why would it be appropriate to
give him this honor? Right, and and then we've all been in
places where you don't give somebody an עלייה Aliyah if they don't
such and such. Right, you know, which seems to run counter to
this. One more time, what was the second point? That there are
lots of כיבודים kibbudim that we don't, that the synagogue won't give
under certain circumstances. But on the one hand, he clearly was a
good guy. He came to report to רבי on this good thing,
so even if he was... well, we won't get into that part
as much, but this sounds like... yeah, because it makes American politics
look tame. Okay, but the other point is I, if you don't
like that, תוספות Tosafot says that the whole... רבי didn't want him,
he sort of felt compelled a little bit to respect the fact
that what this guy came and he reported whatever, but he didn't
want him to lead the בענטשין bentshing and he was trying to
buy him off. He was hoping he would take the money. But
he felt compelled to show a sign, right, and was willing to
go with it. Right, and he didn't accept your לשון הרע lashon
hara about this guy who comes to the door and they say
he's a מין, but clearly he wasn't. Oh, you see, מין, that's
why here it's not just like about what do I think when
I'm reading my philosophy books, and there we're talking about a sect
of Jewish Christians, so it was known who's part of one sect
and who's part of another, I think that that was the case
over here.
Would רבי ply
like a banquet or a more formal type of meal
than a regular סעודה seudah if you'd given people? You would have
wine for בענטשין, bentshing, it would be like...
Yeah, so that's a question, whether you have wine whenever you have
a זימון, do you have wine only when you at least, yeah,
at least when you have a מנין minyan there you would do
it, but sometimes according to some you have wine every time you
do a זימון. So okay, I will just say one last thing
which is that actually this is brought להלכה, le-halakhah, this question about
if somebody steals a ברכה from somebody else or a מצוה mitzvah
at least with ברכות, but anyway, a מצוה mitzvah from somebody else,
paying him a fine. Some people understand that this idea of ten
זוזים zuzim is a fixed fine and you would really alleviate it
at all times. Some say that it would be assessed by the,
you know, any בית דין beit din at the time to assess
what an appropriate fine is, and then gets into other questions about
do we impose fines nowadays, do our court systems, you know, are
we empowered, a Jewish court, to impose fines as opposed to, as
opposed to just, you know, compensatory payment. So תוספות Tosafot raise that
question as well, but this is actually brought in שלחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch and discussed in שלחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. Wait, you had a
question?
Yeah, take a look, אבא
דוגלא Abba Dougla and רחביה, Rechevayah, yeah.
It's my impression, this thing about כוס של ברכה kos shel beracha
and drinking from it, not making a ברכה, that כוס של ברכה
אתה שותה, kos shel beracha atah shoteh, and I know from the
story with ילתא Yalta when I was working on the... Oh, right.
Then there was
an,
it was almost like an amulet thing, a סגולה. segulah. Right,
to drink the כוס של ברכה. kos shel beracha. It was like
a superstition about drinking from...
Yeah, there definitely could be.
But then it's not exactly, I know, but then it's not exactly
parallel. The גמרא Gemara is bringing this to show that you go
by ברכות and because of מצות. mitzvot.
I understand,
I know, so I know, I pointed that out, it is, there
is a problem there and it is discussed, because then it does,
that is what it sounds like, that's what רש"י Rashi sounds like,
but then it's not exactly parallel.
But he's saying to this guy...
I understand, I got it, I got it, I'm just saying that
it's then it does... it's not exactly parallel to the previous discussion,
which is why... Yeah, exactly. Okay, one... yes, and we do have
to move on, go ahead.
On a level of symbolism, he was saying you're concerned about the
Christian... he says, the רבי says it's all one. And then the
other fellow asks for three days.
Right, I was thinking about the three days, I was thinking about
that, the trinity, and then the three days fast to counteract it,
you know.
Yeah, yeah, I was thinking about that, I was thinking about that.
Okay, of course if we're talking about the Christian symbolism, then drinking
from the wine also has some symbolism,
I don't know what to do with that.
Anyway, anyway, okay, we're going to move on, although I'm still going
to make one very last point. תוספות Tosafot says what does it
mean to steal a מצוה mitzvah from somebody? It has to be
particularly your מצוה. mitzvah So for example, and this is where it's
brought up in שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, if I'm... if I have
a son for ברית מילה, brit milah, and I'm going to do
the מילה milah myself and somebody comes in and does the מילה
milah on my son, they stole the מצוה mitzvah from me. But
if I give it to a מוהל mohel and some other מוהל
mohel elbows him out and does it instead, it's never really that
מוהל'ס mohel's מצוה, mitzvah it's only my מצוה. mitzvah So even though
I've assigned the מוהל, mohel, it never becomes his מצוה mitzvah that
he has now a טענה ta'anah that somebody else took it from
him. That's an interesting question about the... what about the second מוהל?
mohel? You, I have a טענה ta'anah against the second מוהל, mohel,
but the first מוהל mohel doesn't.
It never became... Or תוספות Tosafot says if somebody
gets called for
an עלייה, Aliyah,
or let's say the גבאי gabbai said to somebody what's your name,
and he's going to call him for an עלייה, Aliyah,
and somebody else stood up and took the עלייה, Aliyah, תוספות Tosafot
interestingly says it was never his עלייה. Aliyah. You don't like... it's
not like it's your מצוה, mitzvah you were going to get an
honor, and I might have bumped ahead and took the honor instead
of you, but it's not like you owned that מצוה, mitzvah you
owned that honor that somebody else now has stolen it from you.
Although there's an interesting... maybe if you bought the עלייה Aliyah would
be different. Yeah. But this בת קול, bat kol, it's not to
say that a heaven...
I know. So that is an interesting point as well. You're right.
שאול ליברמן Saul Lieberman pointed out that certainly in the ירושלמי... Yerushalmi...
you know, it just became like a public
proclamation or not even like somebody stood up and proclaimed it as
much as like, you know, you know, it became like what? The
not even the moral of the story like, you know, like, right,
right, right, the lesson but, that's not what I'm trying to say.
I'm trying to say yes it means that it was discussed, meaning
that, you know, sort of like yes the moral of the story,
but the moral that everybody learned, meaning afterwards, you know, everybody said,
oh, a thing costs 40 זהובים zuhuvim or you know, so it's
like was it was what became the it was what became the
common discourse, right, it was sort of what became the common discourse
as opposed to some heavenly voice. Because בת קול bat kol is
בת קול bat kol after all. Yeah, that could be also. All
right. ווייטער. weiter. All right. Too much fun. ווייטער. weiter. כיסהו ונתגלה.
kisso venitkalo. You covered it and it got uncovered.
אמר ליה רב אחאי בריה דרבא לרב אשי.
amar leh
Rav Achai
b'rei deRava leRav Ashi.
מאי שנא מהשבת אבידה? mai shna mehashavat aveida? Why if it got
uncovered you do not have to cover it again? How is it
different than returning a lost object? דאמר מר, de'amar mar, because we've
taught, השב, hashev, return, it says the פסוק and we דרשה drasha
is אפילו מאה פעמים, afilu me'ah pe'amim, even if the object keeps
on getting lost, you got to keep on returning. Maybe. So אמר
ליה, he said, התם לא כתיב מיעוטא, hatam lo ktiv mi'uta, there
there is no limiting word. הכא כתיב מיעוטא, hacha ktiv mi'uta, here
there is a limiting word. וכסהו, vechisahu, you shall cover it, which
has a sense of it meaning only it and not not other
things and not multiple times. So anyway, we learn from the we
learn that you do it once and you're done. כיסהו הרוח, kisso
haruach, it was covered
by wind, then it was never actually a מצוה mitzvah?
was never done to
it, so then you have to cover it. But אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Yochanan, לא שנו אלא שחזר ונתגלה, lo shanu ela shechazar venitkaleh, it's
only if now it's revealed. There's no point of covering blood that's
already covered. אבל לא חזר ונתגלה פטור מלכסות, aval lo chazar venitkaleh
patur milchasot, you're exempt and you don't even have to uncover it.
So basically your obligation to cover is if you have unexposed blood
that has not had the מצוה mitzvah of covering done to it.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, וכי חזר ונתגלה מאי הוי,
vechi chazar venitkaleh mai havei, who cares if it became revealed again?
האידחיה ליה, haidcheleh, there was a time where it was excluded from
the מצוה. mitzvah So since there was a period that this blood
the מצוה mitzvah could not have been done to it, so even
if now it
can be done
to it, it should be considered pushed off. And pushed off and
therefore if you remember the concept of דיחוי dichuy by קרבנות, korbanot,
if there's a time an animal can't be brought as a קרבן,
korban, then even if it becomes fit again, it remains invalid. So
if there was a time this blood could not be a מצוה
mitzvah, could not be done to it, it should remain inappropriate for
the מצוה mitzvah even when it becomes revealed. So אמר רב פפא,
amar Rav Pappa, so said רב פפא, Rav Pappa, זאת אומרת אין
דיחוי אצל מצות, zot omeret ein dichuy etzel mitzvot, from here we
see that a דיחוי dichuy is a concept by sacrifices not by
מצות. mitzvot. ומאי שנא מהא דתניא, umai shna mehatanya, and why is
it different than that which we learned, השוחט ונבלע דם בקרקע חייב
לכסות, hashochet venivla dam bakarka chayav lechasot, that if the blood gets
absorbed into the ground you still have to cover? How is that
any different than if the blood is covered by the you know
the wind covers it with dust? So the גמרא gemara says no,
התם כשרשומו ניכר, hatam kshe'rishumo nikar, it's absorbed but you still see
the stain. Since the stain that's still considered to be exposed. But
if it's covered and you don't even see the stain, then you
don't do it. So this principle though of אין דיחוי אצל מצות
ein dichuy etzel mitzvot we're going to see is going to apply
to the next משנה. mishna. Now I should say there's two levels
of אין דיחוי ein dichuy by מצות. mitzvot. One is blood is
funny. Blood is not like a מצוה mitzvah. object the same way
let's say a שופר or a לולב lulav is. There's a whole
גמרא gemara in סוכה Sukkah that talks about let's say there's a
time that I can't use my הדס. hadas. It says if a
הדס hadas is covered with berries, you know berries grow on the
הדס, hadas, it's invalid. What if I pluck the berries? Okay, does
it become valid? Do we say that since when יום טוב Yom
Tov started it couldn't be used, it was נדחה, nidcheh, it was
invalid, it remains invalid even now that I pluck the berries and
now it becomes usable? Is there דיחוי dichuy or not דיחוי dichuy
the same way there's דיחוי dichuy by קרבנות? korbanot? By קרבן korban
we understand it more. If something is holy and sanctified and so
on, the fact that at one time it's pushed off might be
seen as some compromise of its you know of its sanctity. But
something that's a מצוה mitzvah object maybe less and that's the question
does דיחוי dichuy only apply by קרבנות korbanot which have higher standards
and sanctity or does it even apply by מצוה objects? But even
there I could understand that I could say that the הדס hadas
is no longer valid. But by the blood it's not like it's
a מצוה object, right? It's like because there's blood I do the
מצוה of covering. If anything maybe the מצוה object is the dirt,
I don't know. But you know but it's not so much that
I call it a מצוה object that I can say does it
remain it's not like anybody would say the same way there's הלכות
halachot of here's what your אתרוג etrog have to look like to
be a kosher אתרוג, etrog, here's what your blood has to look
like to be kosher blood for the מצוה of כיסוי הדם. kisuy
hadam. It's not the same concept of a מצוה object so that's
why דיחוי dichuy might be least relevant to blood even if it
is maybe relevant possibly relevant to other מצוה objects. Okay so we'll
see more about that as we continue today's דף. Let's take a
look at the next משנה. mishna דם שנתערב במים, dam shenitarav bemayim,
blood gets mixed up with water. To what degree is it still
considered blood? אם יש בו מראה דם חייב לכסות, im yesh bo
mareh dam chayav lechasot, if it still looks like blood you have
to cover. Now תוספות Tosafot by the way says what does it
mean still looks like blood? Does it mean it still is blood
has a bloodish look? or just it still look like blood? There's
a big difference. Right, if you have a little bit of blood
and a lot of water, it's still it's reddish and you could
detect the blood, but for it to still look like real blood,
not just to be detectable, then it has to be only a
little bit of water. Once you have any significant amount of water,
it looks like reddish liquid, but it doesn't look like blood. So
תוספות Tosafot actually says it has to really look like blood, and
therefore only if actually most of these cases are when the water
is in the minority. He says that because he's bothered by the
question that even if it has a reddish look, if the water
was in the majority, why don't we just say laws of ביטול?
bittul? And ביטול bittul will basically say that it no longer matters.
So תוספות Tosafot is assuming in these cases that the water, the
other ingredient is in the minority, and even that might not be
enough because it still has to look like blood. Okay, so it
looks like not just bloody, but it has to look like blood.
This is the laws of מקוה mikvah where we said, you know,
yeah, and okay, this is color versus viscosity? Yes. Yeah, or depth
of color. I mean, it is viscosity, but also if it's very
watered down, then the reddish is a much light, it's a lot
less, you know, it's it's not as deeply red. Especially in terms
of the absorption by the dirt and the ground and the stain
left behind. Blood stays and congeals on the surface of the dirt,
it doesn't sink in, just from the study that we've done, whereas
water, watery blood sinks in. Oh, that's interesting. Okay, so there is
a viscosity to it. Anyway, so if it still is, if it
still looks like blood, not I'll read it like תוספות, Tosafot, not
just not just a little red, not just reddish, but looks really
like blood, then you still have to cover. נתערב ביין, nitarav beyayin,
if it gets mixed with wine, so you can't tell, it's all
red anyway. רואהו כאילו הוא מים, ro'eh oto ke'ilu hu mayim, you
ask yourself if the wine were water, would it still look like
blood? And then you would cover, otherwise no. So the אותו oto
is the wine. נתערב בדם בהמה, nitarav bedam behemah, if it gets
mixed up with the blood of a בהמה, behemah, which is blood
that you don't have to cover, או בדם החיה, o bedam hachayah,
or the blood of a חיה. One minute, I thought you had
to cover the blood of a חיה. So רש"י Rashi says it
means that it's a blood that came out not through שחיטה. The
רמב"ם Rambam says it means that it's a non-kosher חיה, which would
be strange. The רש"ש Rashash has a very nice reading. It doesn't
say בדם חיה, bedam chayah, בדם החיה. bedam hachayah. Can you think
what the difference might mean? החיה hachayah means the blood of a
living animal. And so that's how he reads it, which is basically
like רש"י, Rashi, but it's not a living חיה, it's a living
animal. Anyway, it goes back to Rabbi Yehuda. What? I don't know
what you're saying. Go on. Anyway, רואהו, ro'eh oto, anyway, whatever, some
type of blood, some type of blood which is not blood you
cover, רואהו כאילו הוא מים. ro'eh oto ke'ilu hu mayim. Again, ask
yourself if this other blood were water, would the blood that I'm
חייב chayav to cover still look like blood? And if the answer
is yes, then you're חייב chayav to cover it. רבי יהודה אומר,
רבי יהודה says, אין דם מבטל דם, ein dam mevatel dam, blood
does not nullify blood, even a lot of other blood, you still
have a מצוה to cover. And this is רבי יהודה's, he says
this by קרבנות korbanot as well, and we're going to bring it
in, almost this exact same משנה mishna. was taught by קרבנות. korbanot.
If bloods get mixed up, does one blood nullify another? And the
rabbis say you look at the other blood as if it's water,
and רבי יהודה says bloods don't nullify one another. דם הניתז ושל
הסכין, dam hanitaz veshel hasakin, blood that splatters away from where the
blood was collecting or it's on your knife, חייב לכסות, chayav lechasot,
you have to cover. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, אימתי, eimatai,
when is that true? בזמן שאין שם דם אלא הוא, bizman she'ein
sham dam ela hu, if there's no other blood to cover. אבל
יש שם דם שלא הוא, aval yesh sham dam shelo hu, if
there's other blood that you can do the מצוה with, פטור מלכסות,
patur milachasot, you don't have to cover, which is a very big
question, which I was expecting somebody to ask. Do you have to
cover every single drop of blood, or if you cover some of
the blood, have you done the מצוה? So here at least we're
dealing with a scenario where some of the blood is not immediately
in the location, and that רבי יהודה says if you do it
to the major collection of
blood, you don't have to worry about the other blood.
Let's take a look
at the גמרא, gemara which starts with this question about ביטול. bittul.
תנן התם, tenan hatam, we taught
over there in זבחים, Zevachim, exactly this question about blood getting mixed
up, but there was blood of sacrifices. דם שנתערב במים, dam shenitarav
bemayim, it's almost word for word the same, blood that gets mixed
up with water, אם יש בו מראה דם, im yesh bo mareh
dam, כשר, kasher, if it looks like blood it's כשר kasher and
you can use it to sprinkle on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
So there the word is כשר, kasher, not חייב לכסות. chayav lechasot.
Other than the difference of כשר kasher and חייב לכסות, chayav lechasot,
it's the exact same משנה. mishnah You're looking, you're saying תוספות? Tosafot?
Well, תוספות Tosafot says it has to really have, right, look be
like real blood, right. נתערב ביין, nitarav beyayin, mixed up with wine,
רואהו כאילו הוא מים. ro'eh oto ke'ilu hu mayim. You ask yourself
if the wine were water, would the blood, talk about Christian, if
the wine were water, would the blood,
here we go, wine, water, blood, would the water, would the blood
still look like, still look like blood? Okay. נתערב בדם בהמה, nitarav
bedam behemah, got mixed up with the blood of a בהמה, behemah,
או בדם החיה, o bedam hachayah, and there it could mean חיה
because there the point really is blood that is not קרבן korban
blood, that is not a קרבן, korban, רואהו כאילו הוא מים, ro'eh
oto ke'ilu hu mayim, you see as if it's water, and if
that other blood were water and this the blood you want would
still look like blood, then you can it's כשר kasher you can
sprinkle it. If that if had it been water it would it
would have made it not look like blood, you cannot sprinkle it.
רבי יהודה אומר אין דם מבטל דם.
Rabbi
Yehuda omer ein dam mevatel dam.
No, blood does not nullify blood.
Things are all of the same type, מין במינו, min bemino, of
the same type of material and the same type of liquid or
whatever, one does not nullify the other, you have just a lot
of blood here and therefore since some of it is... blood of
a קרבן korban you sprinkle it, and some of it is blood
of a חיה you cover it, because one does not nullify the
other and you have blood here. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, so said
רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba אמר רבי יוחנן amar
Rabbi Yochanan in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, לא שנו
אלא שנפלו מים לתוך דם. lo shanu ella shenaflo mayim letoch dam.
Very interesting. All of this is true only if the water fell
into the blood and slowly diluted the blood that way. אבל נפל
דם לתוך מים, aval nafal dam letoch mayim, if the blood fell
and it would mean slowly, not in a big you know not
in a big pour, dripped into the water, and every drop of
blood that fell in as it fell in got diluted, and only
after a lot of blood came in were you now able to
see it, now it looked bloody, right you get the scenario, right
you're slowly pouring blood in.
So as it's
going in it's diluted, diluted, doesn't look like blood, it only looks
like blood at the end when all of the blood goes in.
If that were the case, ראשון ראשון בטל, rishon rishon battel, as
each blood goes in it becomes nullified because at that stage it
doesn't look like blood, and therefore even if in the end it
looks like blood it already has stopped to exist and it no
longer has that status. And that's going to be the question. Here
okay let's take a look at the next line. אמר רב פפא
ולעניין כיסוי אינו כן, Amar Rav Papa ul'inyan kisuy eino ken, that's
not true if you have the same scenario when it comes not
to קרבן korban blood but to covering the blood. אין דחוי אצל
מצוות, ein dichuy etzel mitzvot, מצוות are not pushed away. What does
that mean? So this is exactly what מרדכי Mordechai says. When we
say if it's slowly falling in and then at the end of
the day it looks like blood, are we saying it doesn't matter
you don't have blood here? We're saying no. Now you did have
blood, but there was a period where it was slowly falling in
where it lost that status of being blood. That seems to be
what the גמרא gemara is saying. As it's falling in it loses
the status, now that it looks like blood it regains the status
of blood. So it says oh will it matter if something lost
its status and regained it? It matters. If it was sacrificed blood
then it was נדחה, nidcheh, it was pushed away for a while,
for a while it didn't have the status, you can't use it
again. If however it is blood that you're going to cover, we
just said before that even if it was pushed away for a
while now it sits so even if for a while it wasn't
blood now it regained the status of blood and now you would
have to cover it. This becomes a very important question for טריפות.
Treifos. Let's say you had you know חזיר chazer fat falling in
or or יין נסך yayin nesech falling in, drip by drip by
drip it gets בטל, battel, but now at the end it's not
בטל, battel, there's so much wine and you can see it and
so on. So do we say that it stops being wine and
everything is כשר? kosher? Or do we say no, as מרדכי Mordechai
says the phrase is חוזר וניעור, chozer v'ne'or, it wakes up again.
Now that you have enough it now reawakens. So this גמרא seems
to say it does reawaken but because it was asleep for a
while for a קרבן korban that pushed it away, for the מצוה
of covering the blood you still have to do that מצוה of
covering the blood. Okay? Yes. Very conceptual. Well that it disappeared and
came back. So that's why it uses the phrase it woke up.
Okay. It was asleep. It was neutralized for a while. Until it
gets to be critical mass. No, but it's hard to conceptualize the
idea that blood didn't exist and then all of a sudden it
existed. But but but it is the concept okay critical mass. Right.
I think that's why the גמרא uses the phrase of חוזר וניעור,
chozer v'ne'or, like see it more like it was neutralized or asleep.
Okay.
It was it was it was impotent.
Yes. Why wouldn't this principle be the winning argument regarding a calf
born from a שחוטה shechted mother? Oh we're back to that. Why?
I don't understand. Because if if there's no permanent rejection of the
מצוה and אין דחוי אצל מצוות, ein dichuy etzel mitzvot, then once
it comes to look like a living animal again, even though its
legal status from inside the mother is that it was שחוטה shechted
but once it's out and it looks like it's living, I mean
it doesn't only look like it's living. Yeah, but that was first
of all there we weren't saying here we're saying that you have
the opportunity to do a מצוה, there actually saying it's already כשר.
kosher. You have the opportunity to do a מצוה there also you
could שחט the calf. But why should you need to? It was
already שחוטה. shechted. Why should you need to? Because you already were
מבטל mivattel the the דם. dam. No, I there's a difference between
whether something can be used for a מצוה. There anyway the lens
look this is why people like getting to כיסוי הדם kisuy hadam
because we start talking about מצוות. Until now even though you make
a ברכה on שחיטה right the lens was about שחיטה the מתיר
matir as an act that makes the meat כשר. kosher. It wasn't
the lens of מצוה so it was just a we could talk
more about it but that's the basic difference. Let's read a few
more lines. Okay. So the גמרא says, אמר רב פפא ולעניין Amar
Rav Papa ul'inyan oh we just did that. אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל כל מראה אדמומית מכפרים. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel kol mareh
admumit mechapperin. Any any red appearance works for כפרה kapparah for blood
of sacrifice. By the way this sounds not like תוספות, Tosfos, this
sounds like even if it has just a reddish look doesn't really
look like blood. ומכשירים, Umachshirin, it does הכשר זרעים hechsher zerayim if
it falls on you know fruit or whatever it makes it susceptible
for טומאה tumah because one of the things that fruit has to
come in contact with liquid but blood is one of the liquids.
וחייבין בכיסוי V'chayavin bekisuy and you have to cover it, cover it
if it gets into these mixtures. So מאי קא משמע לן? mai
ka mashma lan? What's what's חידוש chiddush is this? מכפרים תנינא Mechapperin
tanina that you can use it for כפרה kapparah for קרבנות korbanot
we taught that, that was the משנה mishna that we quoted that
you use it for sacrifices if it gets mixed up and still
looks red. And וחייבין בכיסוי תנינא, v'chayavin bekisuy tanina, מכפרים תנינא mechapperin
tanina hold on, מכפרים תנינא וחייבין בכיסוי תנינא. mechapperin tanina chayavin bekisuy
tanina. And we taught in our משנה that you cover the blood
if it looks red. So what he said, oh if it looks
red you still cover it, you still use it for כפרה. kappara.
Of course, those are משניות. mishnayos. So מכשירין machshirin איצטריכא ליה. itztricha
lei. No, he was telling me about that if it gets mixed
up with water and other things, it can still make food susceptible
for טומאה. tumah. So the גמרא says מכשירין נמי, machshirin nami, what
big חידוש chiddush is that? Who cares? Blood is getting mixed up
with water. Either one is a liquid. So אי דם, ei dam,
if you would call it blood, אכשורי מכשר, achshurei machshir, it would
make the food susceptible. אי מיא, ei maya, if you call it
water, אכשורי מכשר, achshurei machshir, it would make it susceptible. So who
needs you to tell us that rule? So the גמרא says לא
צריכא שנתערבו במי גשמים. lo tzricha shenis'arvu b'mei geshamim. It got mixed
up with rainwater. Rainwater does not make something susceptible unless you actually
want the rainwater to fall on the thing or you've designated the
rainwater for a use. But if it just happens naturally that rainwater
falls on it, it would not. So this blood got mixed up
with rainwater and then it fell on fruit. If you treat it
like blood, it's מכשיר machshir because this law of having to designate
or to want doesn't apply to other liquids. But if you treated
it as rainwater, it wouldn't because it has not been wanted or
designated. So if so that's why it matters. So the גמרא says
nevertheless, מי גשמים נמי, mei geshamim nami, even rainwater, כיון דשקיל ורמי,
keivan d'shakil v'rami, the גמרא thought that you consciously mixed the rainwater
with the blood. So if you took it and cast put it
in the vessel, אחשובינהו, achshavineihu, you've given it status. So therefore even
rainwater if you're mixing it with blood, the water itself now because
you're giving it significance is fit to make to be מכשיר. machshir.
But it says לא צריכא שנתערבו מאליהן. lo tzricha shenis'arvu mei'aleihen. It
happened by itself. You had a bucket of blood out there and
you left it out in the rain and the rainwater got mixed
in and then it was knocked over and it hit a fruit.
So if you were to consider it rainwater, it wouldn't be מכשיר
machshir because you never gave it status. If you consider it blood,
it is מכשיר. machshir. Okay, and I think we are going to
end here. Not bad. Very close to being caught up. Okay, even
with even with.